Preliminary Guide to the Ernestine Friedl Papers, circa 1950 - 2000
Duke University. University Archives
Ernestine Friedl papers circa 1950 - 2000
Friedl, Ernestine, 1920-
22.5 linear feet Extent: 15000 Items
Duke University. University Archives
Ernestine Friedl served as chair of the Dept. of Anthropology and as Dean of Arts and Sciences and Trinity College at Duke University. She studied gender roles, rural life in modern Greece, and the Chippewa. The Ernestine Friedl papers include personal and professional correspondence, subject files, course materials, articles, reprints, field notes, and sound recordings related to her anthropological research and her roles as professor and administrator at Queens College and Duke University. English.
UA.29.02.0072
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Unprocessed materials are closed pending processing.
Provenance
The Ernestine Friedl Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 2004.
Biographical Note
Personal Information: Born August 13, 1920, in Szegled, Hungary; U.S. citizen; daughter of Nicholas and Ethel (Neudorfer) Friedl. Education: Hunter College (now Hunter College of the City University of New York), A.B., 1941; Columbia University, Ph.D., 1950. Memberships: American Anthropological Association (fellow; president, 1975), American Academy of Arts and Sciences (fellow), American Association for the Advancement of Science (fellow), American Ethnological Society (president, 1967), Northeastern Anthropological Association (president, 1971), Phi Beta Kappa.
Awards: Fulbright and Wenner-Gren Foundation Award, for Vasilika, 1955-56; National Science Foundation grant, 1964-67; Duke University Medal for Distinguished Meritorious Service, 2004.
Career: Wellesley College, instructor in anthropology, 1944-46; Queens College of the City University of New York, 1947-74, assistant professor, 1955-61, associate professor, 1962-65, professor of anthropology, 1965-74, chair of department, 1964-68, executive officer of Ph.D. program in anthropology, 1969-70; Duke University, professor of anthropology, 1973-, chair of department, 1973-78, dean of Arts and Sciences and Trinity College, 1980-1985.
Writings: Vasilika: A Village in Modern Greece, Holt, 1962. Women and Men: An Anthropologist's View, Holt, 1975. Contributor of articles and reviews to American Anthropologist, Human Organization, and Anthropological Quarterly. Edited the Journal of Modern Greek Studies.
[Adapted from: Contemporary Authors Online, Gale, 2005. Reproduced in Biography Resource Center. Farmington Hills, Mich.: Thomson Gale, 2005.]
Collection Overview
The Ernestine Friedl papers include personal and professional correspondence, subject files, course materials, articles, reprints, field notes, and sound recordings related to her anthropological research and her roles as professor and administrator at Queens College and Duke University.
Subject Headings
Friedl, Ernestine, 1920-; Duke University. Dept. of Anthropology; Duke University. Trinity College of Arts and Sciences; Duke University -- Administration; Duke University -- Faculty; Anthropology -- Study and teaching; Gender; Sex role; Greece -- Study and teaching; Microfilm; Sound recordings
Contents of Collection
- Accession, 2004 [A2004-68]
  - Confidential files (Box 1)
  - Readings, articles written by others (Box 1)
  - Sex role course and women's materials (Box 1)
  - Reprints (Box 1)
  - Journal of Sex Role Research (Box 1)
  - Greek Journals (Box 1)
  - Field documents and notes, 1955-1958 (Box 1)
  - Sexuality (Box 2)
  - Teaching Anthropology (Box 2)
  - Feminism and the Classics (Box 2)
  - Terms in Gender Studies (Box 2)
  - Notebooks (Box 2)
  - Sound recordings (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1985-1992 (Box 3)
  - Sex the Invisible, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Field notes (Box 3)
  - Vasilika correspondence (Box 3)
  - Notebooks (Box 3)
  - Sound recordings (Box 3)
  - Microfilm: Greek field notes, 1955-1956 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, general, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, Athens, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
  - Maps (Box 4)
  - Personal, 1983-1984 (Box 4)
  - Farrington, V. (Box 5)
  - Greece trip (Box 5)
  - American Anthropological Association (Box 5)
  - Personal, 1979-1982 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1992-1993, 1997 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1990-1996 (Box 6)
  - Field notes (Box 6)
  - AAA Resource Development Planning Group (Box 6)
  - Course materials (Box 6)
  - Course materials (Box 7)
  - Readings, articles by others (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1998 (Box 7)
  - Friedl archive and digital library (Box 7)
  - Ethics committee (Box 7)
- Addition, 2004 [A2004-78]
  - Correspondence, 1970s and 1980s (Box 8)
  - Clippings (Box 8)
  - Dean of Trinity College of Arts and Sciences (Box 8)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences (Box 8)
  - Unpublished writings (Box 8)
  - Book reviews (Box 8)
  - Dissertation drafts (Box 8)
  - National Humanities Center (Box 8)
  - Spindler book, 1970-1975 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence (Box 9)
  - Reprints, publications, articles, reviews (Box 9)
  - Alaska, summer 1987 (Box 9)
  - Condolence notes (Box 9)
  - Ethnology notes (Box 9)
  - Powdermaker session, AAA 1989 (Box 9)
  - Katherine Verdery (Box 9)
  - AAA papers "in my honor," 1993 (Box 9)
  - Curriculum vitae (Box 9)
  - MLA Role of advocacy (Box 9)
  - Women: American, Australian, bibliographies (Box 10)
  - Sex roles (Box 10)
  - Gender hierarchies (Box 10)
  - Micropolis village community (Box 10)
  - Field notes, notebooks, circa 1976 (Box 10)
  - Writings (Box 10)
  - Vasilika (Box 11)
  - Film materials (Box 11)
  - Course, teaching materials, Duke and Harvard (Box 11)
  - Phi Beta Kappa (Box 11)
  - Greece (Box 12)
    - Scholarly publications (Box 12)
    - Sex roles (Box 12)
    - Culture traits (Box 12)
  - Reprints (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, administrative, professional, and personal, 1960s and 1970s (Box 13)